guys I think this is a cool one I want
to show you the steps of this proof that
3 is equal to Pi let's see if you can
spot the mistake when it happens so
we're going to start with x equals pi
plus 3 over 2. and first we multiply
both sides by 2. on the left hand side
we have 2X and on the right hand side
these twos cancel so we're left with pi
plus 3. and then from here let's
multiply both sides by pi minus 3. so on
the left hand side we're going to
distribute we have pi times the 2x which
is equal to 2 pi x and we have the
negative 3 times the 2x which is equal
to negative 6X and on the right hand
side this is a difference of two squares
anytime you have a plus b times a minus
B it's just a squared minus B squared or
in this case pi squared minus 3 squared
or in other words pi squared minus 9.
next let's subtract this 2 pi x from
both sides and let's add 9 to both sides
on the left hand side these cancel so
we're just left with 9 minus 6X and on
the right hand side these cancel so
we're left with pi squared minus 2 pi x
and then let's add x squared to both
sides of the equation then let's
rearrange the order of a couple of these
this is a perfect square trinomial it
ends up being x minus 3 squared if we
multiply x minus 3 times x minus 3 it
brings us back to this and same thing
here this is also a perfect square
trinomial it ends up being x minus pi
squared and if we multiply x minus pi
times x minus Pi it brings us back to
this and now from this step let's square
root both sides on the left hand side
the square and the square root cancel
each other out so we have x minus 3. and
on the right hand side the square and
the square root cancel each other out so
we have x minus Pi we end up with x
minus 3 equals x minus pi and from here
we subtract X from both sides on the
left hand side we have negative 3 and on
the right hand side we have negative pi
after we divide both sides by negative
one we get three equals pi and clearly
this is not true so where is the mistake
and if you want to try to find the
mistake on your own positive because I'm
going to show it in three two one the
mistake in this occurs right here going
from this step to this step so the
square and the square root don't just
cancel out and give you what's in the
parentheses they always give you the
positive of what's inside the
parentheses so the correct thing would
be to put both sides of the equation in
absolute value and we can actually work
with this so we do know what x is equal
to X is equal to this pi plus 3 over 2
and that is approximately equal to 3.07
so if we plug in 3.07 here this inside
will be positive which means we don't
need the absolute value symbols but if
we plug in 3.07 into this one this
inside the brackets will be negative so
before we get rid of the absolute value
symbols we need to take the negative of
this and that will turn the whole thing
positive and now let's work through this
on this side we can bring down the x
minus 3 and then on the right hand side
this negative distributes to give us
Negative X and then negative times
negative pi is equal to positive Pi
let's add X to both sides and add 3 to
both sides on the left hand side the
threes cancel which gives us 2X and on
the right hand side the X's cancel which
gives us pi plus 3 and after we divide
both sides by 2 we get X is equal to pi
plus 3 over 2. well we already knew that
so in reality we didn't accomplish
anything with all this work we just
apply to operations and then they're
inverses and it brought us back to where
we started did but we did successfully
find the mistake in this proof of 3
equals pi and that was in this step
right here how exciting